Instead, it is that both macro-level and micro-level peacebuilding are needed to make peace sustainable, and local nongovernmental organizations, local authorities and civil society representatives should be the main actors in the bottom-up process. So of course, there are obstacles. Local actors often lack the funding and sometimes the logistical means and the technical capacity to implement effective, local peacebuilding programs. So international actors should expand their funding and support for local conflict resolution. As for Congo, what can be done? After two decades of conflict and the deaths of millions, it's clear that we need to change our approach. Based on my field research, I believe that international and Congolese actors should pay more attention to the resolution of land conflict and the promotion of inter-community reconciliation. So for instance, in the province of the Kivus, the Life and Peace Institute and its Congolese partners have set up inter-community forums to discuss the specifics of local conflicts over land, and these forums have found solutions to help manage the violence. That's the kind of program that is sorely needed throughout eastern Congo. It's with programs like this that we can help people like Isabelle and her husband. So these will not be magic wands, but because they take into account deeply rooted causes of the violence, they could definitely be game-changers. Thank you. (Applause)
Sin embargo, la paz tanto en el ámbito macro como micro es necesaria para lograr una paz sostenible, y las organizaciones no gubernamentales locales, las autoridades locales y los representantes de la sociedad civil deberían ser los principales protagonistas del proceso de abajo arriba. Luego, por supuesto, hay obstáculos. Los protagonistas locales a menudo no tienen ni el capital y a veces tampoco la logística ni la capacidad técnica para desarrollar programas de pacificación de manera eficaz. Los actores internacionales deben ampliar la financiación y el apoyo para la resolución de conflictos locales. En cuanto al Congo, ¿qué se puede hacer? Después de dos décadas de conflicto y millones de muertos, está claro que tenemos que cambiar nuestro enfoque. Basándome en mi investigación de campo, creo que los actores internacionales y congoleños deberían prestar más atención a la resolución de conflictos por la tierra y a la promoción de la reconciliación intercomunitaria. Por ejemplo, en la provincia de los kivu, el Instituto Vida y Paz y sus socios congoleños crearon foros intercomunitarios para discutir los detalles del conflicto por la tierra, y en estos foros se han encontrado soluciones para ayudar a controlar la violencia. Se necesita urgentemente este tipo de programas en todo el este de Congo. Es con programas como estos que podemos ayudar a la gente como Isabelle y su marido. No son varitas mágicas, sino que tienen en cuenta las causas profundamente arraigadas de la violencia y podrían ser definitivamente un punto de inflexión. Gracias. (Aplausos)